RICHA VERMA

Software Engineer | Ex-IBM | Houston, TX | 919-656-6209

richa.verma.kz@gmail.com| linkedin.com/in/richa-verma | github.com/richa-verma1001 | rverma-portfolio

CAREER PROFILE

15 years of fullstack software development experience with IBM; 5 years of experience in frontend stack React, Node.js Worked as a Technical Lead on 3 key IBM Projects **Awards:** IBM Outstanding Achievement Award, IBM UX Champion Award; **Patent:** Visual Representation of erroneous fields; **Certification:** PMI Agile Foundations Practitioner

EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Engineer | FullStack Developer | Suburban Propane | Whippany, NJ Aug 2021 - June 2023

- Designed and developed client application using MERN Stack (MongoDB, Express, React and Node.js)
- Developed microservices using REST framework and Springboot, used Bootstrap with React to create application
- Implemented RFP (Request for Proposal) microservice to provide RESTful API utilizing Springboot
- Created custom docker images, tagging, pushing images, integrating with Spring boot application.
- Used agile methodology and attended daily scrums and weekly retrospectives

Senior Software Engineer | Technical Lead | Agile Coach | IBM | Watson | Houston, TX Aug 2015 - Jun 2018

- Led a team of 8 developers for successful delivery of Watson Company Analyzer on IBM Cloud platform.
- Facilitated project planning, collaborating with stakeholders to refine requirements and prioritize product backlog.
- Worked with design for early feedback on wireframes, enhancing UI, leading to higher customer satisfaction.
- Delivered a fully responsive, high performance React application, leveraging Webpack, React, Node.js, Javascript
- Integrated analytics, tracking events, usage & page views, reporting KPIs for actionable insights to stakeholders.
- Utilized docker and kubernetes to containerize applications & orchestrate deployments for scaling.
- Developed features, led daily scrums, conducted code review, sprint planning and retrospectives while continuously collaborating with stakeholders, optimizing team performance and creating a culture of growth.

Advisory Software Engineer | Technical Lead | IBM | Connections | San Francisco, CA Jan 2010 - Aug 2015

- Led a global team of 10 developers, successfully delivering multiple product releases for IBM Connections.
- Received Outstanding Achievement Award for leading successful integration of IBM Mail into Connections.
- Managed client crit-sits, driving open issues to closure and ensuring effective stakeholder communication.
- Developed robust RESTful APIs (JAVA), facilitating seamless frontend-backend data exchange and integration.
- Enabled full test coverage (Mocha), automation testing(Selenium) and continuous integration pipelines(Jenkins)
- Enhanced brand and market presence by publishing articles & delivering presentations at yearly IBM Conference.

Software Engineer | IBM | Lotus Quickr | Raleigh, NC

Oct 2004 - Dec 2010

- Developed Eclipse IDE wizard in Java to generate custom form instances(XML, XFORMS) for mobile rendering.
- Developed customizable product themes and multiple portlet applications using Java, Javascript and Dojo.
- Received UX Champion Award for increased customer satisfaction with continuous stakeholder engagement

FREELANCE July 2018 - June 2021

A career pause for an expat relocation. Repatriated and excited to return to work

- Published 20+ web applications as demonstrated in <u>Portfolio</u>
- Developed multiple React and vanilla javascript applications. Completed certifications: React 18; PMI Agile Foundations; Cert Prep: PMI Agile Practitioner

SKILLS

Technical: Java, React, Node.js, Javascript, ES6, JSON, HTML, CSS, SASS, Jest, Mocha, Selenium, Webpack, REST, PostgreSQL, MySQL, JIRA, Jenkins, Docker, Kubernetes; **Leadership:** Team Management, Stakeholder Management, Collaboration, Problem Solving, Adaptability, Team Work, Innovation, Agile Methodologies, Scrum, GitHub

EDUCATION

North Carolina State University, Bachelors in Computer Science (Summa Cum Laude)